A Finding Aid to the Hughie Lee-Smith Papers, circa 1890-2007, bulk 1931-1999, in the Archives of American Art AAA.leeshugh
Archives of American Art
Hughie Lee-Smith papers
bulk 1931-1999
circa 1890-2007
AAA.leeshugh
Archives of American Art
33.3 Linear feet
The papers of painter and educator Hughie Lee-Smith measure 33.3 linear feet and date from circa 1890 to 2007, with the bulk of the material dating from 1931 to 1999. The collection documents Lee-Smith's career through biographical material, personal and professional correspondence, writings by Lee-Smith and others, personal business records, exhibition files, organization records, printed material, scrapbooks, photographs, a small amount of artwork, numerous interviews, and recordings for a documentary film on Lee-Smith. Also found are the papers of artist Rex Goreleigh, a friend of Lee-Smith.
Lee-Smith, Hughie
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
A small amount of material was donated 1969-1981 by Hughie Lee-Smith. Additional papers were donated in 2011 by Patricia Lee-Smith, widow of Hughie Lee-Smith.
Related Archival Materials note
Also found at the Archives of American Art is an oral history interview with Hughie Lee-Smith conducted by Carroll Greene in 1968.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 13 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1890-2001 (1.7 linear feet; Box 1-2, 35, RD 38)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1931-2006 (6.1 linear feet; Box 2-8)
Series 3: Writings, circa 1934-1998 (0.8 linear feet; Box 8-9)
Series 4: Personal Business Records, 1934-2001 (1.6 linear feet; Box 9-11, 35)
Series 5: Exhibition Files, circa 1973-2001 (1.2 linear feet; Box 11-12)
Series 6: Organization Records, 1941-2005 (2.1 linear feet; Box 12-14)
Series 7: Printed Material, 1919, 1930-2007 (8.5 linear feet; Box 14-22, 34)
Series 8: Scrapbooks, circa 1938-1990s (0.2 linear feet; Box 22, 35)
Series 9: Photographs, circa 1890-2003 (4.4 linear feet; Box 22-26, 35, OV 37)
Series 10: Artwork, circa 1940s-1980s (0.2 linear feet; Box 26)
Series 11: Interviews, 1973-1998 (2.1 linear feet; Box 26-28)
Series 12: Documentary Film Materials, 1985-2004 (3.5 linear feet; Box 28-32)
Series 13: Rex Goreleigh Papers, 1935-1994 (0.9 linear feet; 32-33, 36)
Biographical/Historical note
Hughie Lee-Smith (1915-1999) was a painter and educator in Ohio, Michigan, and New York. Born in Eustis, Florida, he lived for a period of time with family in Atlanta before joining his mother in Cleveland, Ohio, in 1925. In 1934 he received a scholarship to attend the Art School of the Detroit Society of Arts and Crafts, and in 1935 returned to Cleveland to attend the Cleveland School of Art. While in school he began exhibiting his paintings and teaching part-time at Karamu House. From 1938 to 1940 Lee-Smith completed lithography commissions for the Ohio WPA. In 1941 he moved to Detroit, married his first wife Mabel Louise Everett, and worked at a Ford automobile factory. He was then drafted into the U.S. Navy as a mural artist. After the war he briefly returned to factory work before enrolling at Wayne State University, earning a degree in Art Education in 1953. From 1953 to 1965 he taught summer art classes at the Grosse-Point War Memorial in Detroit.
In 1957 Lee-Smith moved to the East Village in New York City, signed with the Janet Nassler Gallery (Petite Gallery), exhibited his work extensively, and joined several art organizations. He also taught art at schools in Princeton, New Jersey. In 1967 he became the second African-American member of the National Academy of Design. He was visiting instructor and artist-in-residence at several art programs, including Howard University, and taught at the Art Students League from 1972 to 1988. In 1978 he married his third wife, Patricia. The New Jersey State Museum organized an extensive retrospective of Lee-Smith's work in 1988 which travelled nationally. Despite ill-health in the mid-1990s, he continued to create new paintings and exhibit his work. In 1997 he moved with his wife to Albuquerque, New Mexico, where he lived until his death in 1999.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of painter and educator Hughie Lee-Smith measure 33.3 linear feet and date from circa 1890 to 2007, with the bulk of the material dating from 1931 to 1999. The collection documents Lee-Smith's career through biographical material, personal and professional correspondence, writings by Lee-Smith and others, personal business records, exhibition files, organization records, printed material, scrapbooks, photographs, a small amount of artwork, numerous interviews, and recordings for a documentary film on Lee-Smith. Also found are the papers of artist Rex Goreleigh, a friend of Lee-Smith.
Biographical material includes records of Hughie Lee-Smith's schooling, military service, and awards, as well as resumes, bibliographies, and biographical summaries. Also found are family records, including the papers of his mother, Alice Carroll.
Lee-Smith's correspondence is with family, students, arts and cultural organizations, as well as schools, galleries, and museums, primarily regarding his participation in events and exhibitions. He also corresponded with fellow artists, such as Clarence Holbrook Carter, Reginald Gammon, Joseph Hirsch, Carol Wald, and Hale Woodruff, among many others. He maintained extensive correspondence with artist Sophie Wessel.
Lee-Smith's writings include artist statements and personal writings on his history and early influences, as well as many draft lectures and speeches, school writings, notes, and untitled writing fragments. Writings by others primarily include student essays and articles on the topic of Lee-Smith's work. Personal business records include scattered financial documents, including artwork sales records, and contracts and agreements with various art galleries and other organizations. Also found are files regarding his art commissions, gifts, professional activities, and records of his employment at the Art Students League. Exhibition files document select exhibitions in which Hughie Lee-Smith participated, primarily during the 1980s and 1990s. Organization records were maintained by Lee-Smith to document his participation in various groups, such as the National Academy of Design, Ira Aldridge Society, and Audubon Artists.
Printed material consists primarily of exhibition announcements and invitations for exhibitions of Lee-Smith's work, as well as news clippings, magazines, press releases, and publications from various art organizations and schools. One scrapbook contains exhibition announcements additional loose scrapbook pages document his early career. Photographs include many portraits of Hughie Lee-Smith, Lee-Smith in his studio, at events, and with friends and family. Additionally there are many photographs, slides, and transparencies of Lee-Smith's artwork. Also found are five photograph albums. A small amount of original artwork includes drawings by Lee-Smith and two sketchbooks belonging to his wife Patricia.
The collection includes numerous interviews of Hughie Lee-Smith, recorded on 37 sound cassettes, one sound tape reel, and four video cassettes. Also found are planning documents, research material, and video footage for a documentary about the life and work of Hughie Lee-Smith, produced by New Deal Films, Inc, but never completed. Footage includes interviews with artists and art historians regarding Lee-Smith, gallery events, and images of his paintings.
The papers of artist Rex Goreleigh primarily documents his later life and includes a letters, biographical documents, printed material, estate records, and photographs and slides depicting Goreleigh, his studio, and artwork. Hughie Lee-Smith was close friends with Goreleigh and served as executor of his estate.
Also of note is a scrapbook put together for Goreleigh's 70th birthday in 1972. Of note is one scrapbook which contains photographs, notes, and artwork by fellow artists and students, including drawings by Romare Bearden and Hughie Lee-Smith.
Art Students League (New York, N.Y.). -- Faculty; Audubon Artists (New York, N.Y.).; Bearden, Romare, 1911-1988; Carter, Clarence Holbrook, 1904-2000; Gammon, Reginald, 1921-2005; Goreleigh, Rex, 1902-; Hirsch, Joseph, 1910-1981; Ira Aldridge Society.; National Academy of Design (U.S.).; Wald, Carol; Wessel, Sophie; Woodruff, Hale, 1900-1980; African American artists--Michigan; African American artists--New York (State)--New York; Artists' studios--Photographs; Drawings; Educators--Michigan; Educators--New York (State)--New York; Interviews; Painters--Michigan--Detroit; Painters--New York (State)--New York; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sound recordings; Video recordings
- Biographical Material, circa 1890-2001; Series 1; 1.7 Linear feet Box 1-2, 35, RD 38
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material includes records of Hughie Lee-Smith's schooling, service in the military, and various awards which he received throughout his career as an artist. Also found are professional resumes and bibliographies, membership documents, as well as biographical notes gathered for Romare Bearden and Harry Henderson's book History of African American Artists. Additionally there are family records, including scattered papers belonging to Lee-Smith's mother Alice Carroll. Also of note is one sound cassette recording of Lee-Smith's memorial service in 1999.
  Arrangement note
  Files are arranged in alphabetical order by folder title.
  - Alice Carroll Papers, circa 1890-1978 (Box 1, Folder 1-7)
  - Award, Wayne State University, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Award Certificates, 1934-1999 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Oversized material housed in Box 35.
  - Award Plaques, 1981-1997 (Box 1, Folder 10-12)
  - Bearden/Henderson Book Project, Corrections to Biography, 1996; 1993 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bibliography, 1985-1990s (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Biographical Sketch, circa 1957 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Business Cards - "People Hughie Knew", circa 1970s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Celebration of the Black Artist Tribute by the Dedicators, Inc., 1997 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Certificate of Commendation, Department of the Navy, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Christmas Card List, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Cleveland Institute of Art Alumni Reunion, 1993-1998 (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
  - Family Tree, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Guestbooks, 1998; 1987 (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
  - High School Track Letters, 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Honorary Doctorate, Maryland Institute College of Art, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - James Van Der Zee Award, 1993-1999 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - Luggage Keys, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Membership and Identification Cards, circa 1940s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Memorial Service, 1999 May 16; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Military Records, 1940-1945 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Name Tags, 1989-1995 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Passports and Passport Application, 1962; 1977; 1954 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Plans for Studio-Residence, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Oversized material housed in RD 38.
  - Rental Dispute, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Resumes, 1980-2000 (Box 2, Folder 14-16)
  - Senior Class Cap, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Signed Palette from Art Students League Class of 1988 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - "Some Salient Facts of My Life/Career That Have Most Frequently Been Distorted", circa 1990s (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Student Documents, 1949-1952 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Student Records, Wayne State University, 1950-1953 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Travel Wallet, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Unitarian Universalist Church, circa 1950s (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Veterans Administration Records, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Oversized Award Certificates, 1940-1999 (Box 35)
    Oversized material from Box 1, Folder 9.
  - Oversized Plans for Studio-Residence, 1972-1973 (Box OV 38)
    Oversized material from Box 2, Folder 12.
- Correspondence, 1931-2006; Series 2; 6.1 Linear feet Box 2-8
  Found here is Hughie Lee-Smith's personal and professional correspondence, including correspondence with many fellow artists, students and publishers, requests for him to teach, lecture, or write, and business correspondence regarding exhibitions and sales of his work. There are also letters from his mother, father, daughter, and other family members. Also found is correspondence with arts and cultural organizations in which Lee-Smith participated, which may include additional printed material sent out to members. He also corresponded with schools, galleries, and museums, primarily regarding his participation in events and exhibitions.
  Artists that Lee-Smith corresponded with include Clarence Holbrook Carter, Adolphus Ealey, Anthony Eterovich, Reginald Gammon, Rex Goreleigh, Werner Groshans, Joseph Hirsch, Everett Kinstler, Leon Kroll, Joseph Pearson, Louis Redstone, Bob Solotaire, Carol Wald, and Hale Woodruff. Lee-Smith also maintained extensive correspondence with artists Sophie Wessel and Barry Hinchliff. He also corresponded with art historians, collectors, curators, and gallery owners, such as Florence Davies, Carroll Greene, Lewis Tanner Moore, and Lowery Sims.
  In general, letters are filed alphabetically by person or corporate name. Names with four or more letters are filed in their own folders, and the remainder of correspondence is filed in miscellaneous alphabetical files. Some correspondence with individuals may also be filed according to the name of the organization with which they were associated. Drafts of Lee-Smith's outgoing letters are primarily filed together in the first four folders of the series, but additional outgoing letters may be interfiled with incoming letters.
  - Outgoing Letters (Carbon Copies), 1968-1982 (Box 2, Folder 25-28)
  - Adams, Leslie, 1982-1998; 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Alliance for Young Artists and Writers, Inc., 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Allied Artists of America, 1993; 1958-1967 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - American Society of African Culture, 1959-1963 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Archives of American Art, 1963-1989 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Artists Equity Association, 1947-1974 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Art Students League, 1968-1997; 2003 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - A, Miscellaneous, 1943-1997 (Box 2, Folder 36-37)
  - Banneker-Douglas Museum, 1976-1995 (Box 2, Folder 38-39)
  - Barnett Aden Gallery, 1955; 1958 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Blye, Marlene, 1991-2002 (Box 2, Folder 41-42)
  - Bowers, Helen, circa 1964-1971; 1958 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Branch, Brenda, 1968-1995 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Bright, Alfred Lee, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Burr, Dane, 1952-1954 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Burroughs, Margaret, 1985-1987 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Butler Institute of American Art, 1964; 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - B, Miscellaneous, 1938-1998 (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
  - Calabria, Philip, 1996-2001 (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
  - Campbell, Lawrence, 1989-1992 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Campbell, Ruth C., 1991-1997 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Cards from Students (Groups), 1977-1984 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Carroll, Alice, 1957-1977 (Box 3, Folder 11-12)
  - Carter, Clarence Holbrook, 1946; 1988-1992 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Clarke, Richard, 1976-1996 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Cleveland Institute of Art, 1968-1989 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Cleveland Museum of Art, 1938-1956; 1974 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Consumer Correspondence, 1979-1991 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Crazy Horse, Chief Roy, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - C, Miscellaneous, 1934-1999 (Box 3, Folder 19-20)
  - Dallas Museum of Art, 2004-2005 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Davies, Florence, circa 1945-1955 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Davison, Dr. Henry, circa 1993-1996 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Delgado, Dorothy and Gilmore, circa 1944-1968 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Department of the Navy, 1971-1979 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Detroit Artists Market, 1957-1989 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Detroit Institute of Arts, 1998; 1951-1977 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Detroit Public Library, 1951-1955 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Dyyon, Frazier, 1996; 1992 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - D, Miscellaneous, 1934-2000 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Ealey, Adolphus, 1982-1990 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Ebony Magazine, 1967; 1957 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Edwards, James and Ursula, circa 1990s (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Eterovich, Anthony, 1989-1996 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - E, Miscellaneous, 1934-circa 1985 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Fanning, Robert J., 1963-1994 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Forsythe Gallery, 1958-1971 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Freeman, Mark, 1987-2000 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - French, Elizabeth, 1982-1997 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Fuller, Hoyt, 1954-1969 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - F, Miscellaneous, 1940-1997 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Gammon, Reggie, 1969-2000 (Box 3, Folder 42-44)
  - Gates, Arnold, 1935-1999 (Box 3, Folder 45-49)
  - Get Well Cards, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Goreleigh, Rex, 1945-1979 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Gorman, Bill, 1975-circa 1980s (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Grand Central Art Galleries, 1967-1978 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Grebenak, Louis, 1947-1954 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Greene, Carroll, 1967-1998 (Box 4, Folder 6-8)
  - Groshans, Werner and Yetta, 1983-1989 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Grosse Pointe War Memorial Association, 1977; 1959-1965 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - G, Miscellaneous, 1936-1999 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Hall, Michael, 1993-2000 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Harcourt, Brace and World, Inc., 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Harper Collins/Scott Foresman, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Hawkins, Ida, 1993-1997 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Herzog, Priscilla Jenne, 1988-1999 (Box 4, Folder 16-17)
  - Hewitt, John H. and Vivian, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Hilton, Lawrence, 1983-1991 (Box 4, Folder 19-20)
  - Hinchliff, Barry and Brenda, circa 1963-1997 (Box 4, Folder 21-39)
  - Hirsch, Joseph, 1949-1981 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Holden, Donald, 1938; 1989-1998 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Holton, Curlee, circa 2000-2006 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Houghton Mifflin Company, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Howard University (James Porter), 1949-1971 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Hunter, Bethuel, 1995-1997 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Hynes, Frances, 1993-1994 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - H, Miscellaneous, 1934-2001 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - I, Miscellaneous, 1970-1981 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - June Kelly Gallery, 1994-1997 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - J, Miscellaneous, 1945-1996 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Keene Publishing Corporation, 1969-1970 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Kenkeleba House, 1985-1988 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Kinstler, Everett Raymond, 1987-1997 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Kleinman, Joseph and Maureen Turchi, 1995-1998 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Kraushaar Galleries, 1952-1955 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Kroll, Leon, 1954; 1969 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - K, Miscellaneous, 1945-2000 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Lasnik, Nathan, 1948-1999 (Box 5, Folder 10-12)
  - Lawson, Mabel, 1983-1986 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Leipzig, Mel, 1988-2000 (Box 5, Folder 14-15)
  - Lindsay, June McKee, 1993-1998 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - L, Miscellaneous, 1950-1998 (Box 5, Folder 17-18)
  - Mandel, Howard, 1984-1996 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Marion, Sara L., 2000-2001 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Marquis, Pamela, 1985-1986 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Maryland Commission on Afro-American History and Culture, 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Meet the Masters, 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Michigan Veteran's Trust Fund, 1948-1949 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Mohammed, Ellen, circa 1985-1995 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Moore, Lewis Tanner and Judy Heggestad, 1994-2006 (Box 5, Folder 26-27)
  - M, Miscellaneous, 1945-2000 (Box 5, Folder 28-29)
  - National Academy of Design, 1959-1991 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Nessler, Janet, 1958-1968 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Nguzo Saba Films, Inc., 1979-1982 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Noel, Debbie, 1986-1998 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - N, Miscellaneous, 1944-2005 (Box 5, Folder 34-35)
  - Ogul, Ed, 1995-1996 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Ogunquit Museum of American Art, 1999-2001 (Box 5, Folder 37-38)
  - O'Neal, Frederick, 1969; 1964 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - O, Miscellaneous, 1964-1993 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Pajaud, William, 1964-1965 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Parker, James, 1986-1998 (Box 5, Folder 42-44)
  - Patterson, Stephanie and Don, circa 1978-1990 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Pearlstein, Constance Webb, 1982-1997 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Pearson, Joseph, 1970; 1985-1991 (Box 5, Folder 47-48)
  - Pearson, Joseph, 1992-2004; Includes two CD-Rs containing photographs of recent works. (Box 6, Folder 1-8)
  - Pettigrew, Joy, 1989-1991 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Phillips Mill Community Association, 1989; 1984 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Pittman Galleries, 1981-1984 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - P, Miscellaneous, 1933-1998 (Box 6, Folder 12-13)
  - Redstone, Louis, 1988-2001; 1950 (Box 6, Folder 14-17)
  - Rodgers, Norma, 1991-1995 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Rosenfeld, Michael, 1994-2002 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Ross, David, 1947-1969 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - R, Miscellaneous, 1931-1996 (Box 6, Folder 21-22)
  - Schomberg Center for Research in Black Culture, 1980; 1998-1999 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Seiden, Art, circa 1995-1998 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Sims, Lowery, circa 1989-1996 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Smith, Christina (Daughter), 1959-1996 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Smith, Luther, 1945-1971 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Smithsonian Institution, circa 1995 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Solotaire, Bob, 1967-1999 (Box 6, Folder 29-30)
  - Stella Jones Gallery, 1998-2000 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Student Recommendations, 1983-1989 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Summit Gallery, 1981-1984 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - S, Miscellaneous, 1934-2001 (Box 6, Folder 34-36)
  - Thomas, William and Ruth, 1945-1998 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Thornton Associates, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Turner, Phillip, 1986-1988 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - T, Miscellaneous, 1949-1996 (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - University of Chicago, 1968-1969 (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - University of Michigan, 1956-1966 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - U-V, Miscellaneous, 1942-1994 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Wadsworth Atheneum (Amistad Foundation), 1991-1997 (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - Wald, Carol, 1982-1998 (Box 6, Folder 45-46)
  - Walter W. Newcomer and Associates, 1931 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Wayne State University, 1949-1998 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Welsh, Janet, 1970; 1989-2000 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Wessel, Sophie, 1944-1986 (Box 7, Folder 4-39)
  - Wessel, Sophie, 1987-1994 (Box 8, Folder 1-15)
  - Willis, John, 1976-1979 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Woodruff, Hale, 1943-1947 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - W, Miscellaneous, 1934-1995 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Your Heritage House, Inc., 1978-1982 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Y-Z, Miscellaneous, 1977-1983 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Unidentified, 1943-2000 (Box 8, Folder 21-23)
- Writings, circa 1934-1998; Series 3; 0.8 Linear feet Box 8-9
  This series consists of writings by Hughie Lee-Smith and writings by others about Lee-Smith's career and artwork. Found among Lee-Smith's writings are an artist statement, credo, and other personal writings on his history and early influences. Also included are many draft lectures and speeches for events, school writings, and miscellaneous notes and untitled writing fragments. Writings by others primarily include student essays and articles. Also found is a notebook belonging to his mother, Alice Carroll, and poetry by his second wife, Helen Bowers.
  Writings by Lee-Smith are arranged first within this series followed by writings by others, alphabetical by author's last name.
  - "Credo", circa 1945 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Eulogy for James A. Porter, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Lecture for Art Goes to School (AGTS), 1984-1986 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Lecture Notes, 1950s; 1970s (Box 8, Folder 27-29)
  - "My First Month in East Tech", circa 1930s (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Notes, undated (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Notes on Talk to Detroit Bahais, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - Notes Written on Envelopes, 1950s-1960s (Box 8, Folder 33)